So let me just firstly introduce you to what I mean by that. So logical reason. In Isabelle, there is
a way to use existing lemmas to prove current specifications that you want to prove.
So let me just give you an informal example to motivate that. So suppose
suppose we want to prove that, let's say that given p, we can derive q. And suppose that we have a lemma
that says given, let's say, r, we can have p. And suppose that we have another lemma that says that
we can always derive r without any assumptions. Then we can prove this theorem in a forward way
in the following as follows. So I will just apply modus ponens here. So
informally, we can say that I will just call this 1 and this 2 and this 3. Second, I will just say
from 1, sorry, no, sorry. So 1, what we want to prove is 1. So we can just start like we just,
I'll just start from this one, that one, and then we want to derive this one. So we want to say,
we want to prove that p, we can derive q from p. So how can we do that? We can also say
from 1, we know we deduce that if we can show that r holds, then we can show that q holds.
Why is that? Because r says if we have, because 1 says if we have r, then we can derive p.
And our goal is if we have p, then we can derive q. So this has, so using 1, we can transform our
goal instead of being p, instead of deriving q from p, we can, we transform it to a new goal, which is
r, like we can derive q from r. So that was goal 1, and then now that's goal number 2 after using
this fact. Now we can then transform that goal again by saying, okay, so if we can, if we can,
if we show r, then we can derive q. And we have, we know that we have r. So in this video,
let me show you the first type of logical reasoning, which is forward and backward reasoning,
as shown here in this slide. So let me just show the first type of thing. So logical reasoning
forward and backward, all right? So let's, let me just give you an informal example to
motivate that. Suppose we want to prove the following. We want to show that if we have
that p implies q, and we have that q implies r, and we have that r does not hold, we want to show
that from this we can derive that p does not hold, okay? So informally, what we can, like the way you
can argue that is that saying, okay, if p holds, then q holds, and if q holds, then r holds,
but r doesn't hold, that means that q doesn't hold, that means that p doesn't hold, so this means
that we can derive not p from this, okay? But how can we prove that using forward and backward
reasoning? So we can do the following informal proof, and then I will show you how to do it in
Isabelle, that will be the structure. So firstly, we can, from the assumption, we know that not r holds,
okay? That's from the assumption, and also from the assumption we know that
q implies r, right? That's also from the assumption. Okay, from that we want to derive
that not q. Recall we have this law that is called implication introduction, okay? So it's a lemma,
kind of, right? I mean, in Isabelle, it would be a lemma, and I will show you how. So that law would
say, so this, it's usually written like that, so this would be a lemma. We need this lemma.
We need a lemma that basically says that if you have, if you have some q, then you can always
derive from that p implies q for anything. So if you have q, then p implies q is always
reliable. And what is the rationale behind that? It's the following, okay? So here,
this is any predicate p, and any predicate q, and any predicate p. These are not related
to this one, so maybe I should just do it, like, modify the lemma slightly with x and y. So,
no. If you have x, then you can always from that derive that some y implies x, right? Because you
already know that x holds. So in our case, we can, okay, we can use that lemma, right,
to derive the following from, to derive the following from step number one here. So we can
derive, we can derive from that that q implies not r, and this one, this is from one, and from
this lemma called implication introduction. And here, this logical step is a forward reasoning
step. Why? Because you have, you already have some, you have proved some fact, which is here,
is fact number one, and you have a lemma, and that lemma has an assumption. And then you
instantiate the assumption of the lemma with the fact that you have proved and get,
in return, the conclusion of that lemma. So let me just explain that a bit in more details.
So why is this a forward reasoning? That's because, or how is this a forward reasoning
rather? Not why is this? So how is this forward reasoning step? How is this a forward reasoning
step? That's because we have implication introduction, and that lemma which, and that lemma has an
assumption, and from that lemma, when we instantiate, and we instantiated that assumption,
we instantiated the assumption of that lemma with another fact that we have proved,
which is fact number one, namely fact number one. So that's what it means to a forward reasoning.
And in Isabelle, the notation of having, of representing forward reasoning is as follows.
So in Isabelle, the notation of represent forward reasoning can be done as follows.
If you have two facts, f1 and f2, and you want, let me just write that a bit more clearly,
if you have two facts, f1 and f2, and you want to instantiate an assumption of f2 with f1,
the way you write that in Isabelle is like this, f2 of f1. And that, in our case, for example,
here f2 would be, in our example, f2 is implication introduction, and f1 is fact one. So this is a step
of forward reasoning. So that's number, that's proof step number three. And then in step number
four in our proof, we can derive that Q does not already, if you have, if you remember, there is
also another theorem, like another theorem that says, like, or, you know, maybe you don't remember
that, but I'll just introduce it to you. It's a theorem that's called negation introduction.
And that theorem says that if you, if you, if you have, if Q, if you have, okay, I'll just use X and Y,
so make sure that this is not confused with the symbols we have in our lemma. So if you have,
for example, X implies Y, and X implies not Y, then you know for sure that X does not hold,
because it's impossible that X holds and, you know, because if X does hold, then you have Y and not Y
holding at the same time. So this is another lemma called negation introduction. So from that,
so we can derive number four, step number four here from, from step number two and three,
and negation introduction will again forward reasoning from two, three, and negation introduction.
Forward reasoning. So we instantiated, for example, this assumption with, with two,
and this assumption with three. So like in Isabelle, the notation here would be negation introduction
of two and three. So you're instantiating both assumptions. So now we have derived not Q,
and then we can do the same again to derive not P. So from not Q we can derive
that, we can derive, let me just see that. So we have not Q, then we can derive also that
P implies not Q. This is from four and implication introduction, which is this lemma down there.
Let me just use the laser to point properly to it. So if you remember it, this lemma,
so we use this lemma and this fact to derive that again with forward reasoning.
And then we just do number six, step number six, where we use the assumption, this assumption there,
and that step to derive that P does not hold. So we use, so we have not P from
assumption and step number five and negation introduction. And again, this is
all of these steps of forward reasoning. And then we have our goal proof.
All right. So that's, that's forward reasoning.